Inventory of the Louise Page Morris papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Louise Page Morris papers
1950-1984
95034
Hoover Institution Archives
3 manuscript boxes 1.2 linear feet
Correspondence, reports, memoranda, speeches, notes, and financial records, relating to activities of the Free Trade Union Committee in opposing communist influence in trade unions abroad, especially in Asia and the Middle East, and to political conditions in those regions. Includes extensive correspondence with Jay Lovestone, executive secretary of the Free Trade Union Committee.
Morris, Louise Page.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1995.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
She was born in 1904 in Boston, to Edward and Olga Page. She married once, to John ‘Koko’ Morris, whom she divorced in 1932. Morris began her espionage career as an anti-Soviet counterintelligence agent during WWII. She spoke Russian was recruited to work in the London analyzing information lifted from the Soviets. In 1943 she became the deputy chief of the USSR Research and Analysis Section, Office of Strategic Services (OSS). After the war, Morris worked for OSS chief “Wild” Bill Donovan, who introduced her to Ray Murphy, Communist Expert for the State Department. Mr Murphy asked her to infiltrate the Congress of American Women and determine if it was a communist front group. It was through Ray Murphy that she met Jay Lovestone and began a romance with him that would last over thirty years. Lovestone was working closely with James Jesus Angleton, who would become the CIA’s counterintelligence chief. Impressed with all he had heard about Morris’s successful intelligence work, he propositioned that she be his personal agent, functioning outside the CIA, going on assignments for him to collect intelligence around the world. Her cover was that she worked for Lovestone and the FTUC, operating the “Gompers Research Library” in New York City. Louise Page Morris worked for Mr Angleton until 1974. She died in 2002.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Morris Papers contain correspondence from friends and colleagues received by Morris during her travels, as well as intelligence information produced by the American Federation of Labor’s Free Trade Union Committee (FTUC).
Comprised primarily of personal and professional correspondence, most notably from Jay Loveston. Lovestone was the well-known President of the FTUC and worked closely with Morris’ employer, James Jesus Angleton, the chief of the CIA's Counterintelligence Staff from 1954 to 1975. Lovestone frequently referred to Morris’s work for the CIA and passes covert information to her via codewords.
The collection also contains reports accumulated by Morris, some of which she produced herself, and some by third parties on free labor movements in developing states. Reports by Morris were generally handwritten drafts of weekly or monthly reports sent back to her employer, James Angleton. Also included are notes taken during meetings with individuals of interest. These were often written on small scraps of paper or on the backsides of other printed material. Morris collected correspondence, reports, manuscripts, and transcripts from third parties. Such papers were often not addressed to her but copies of correspondence between international actors and the FTUC or written to supplement her collection of intelligence.
The Reports Series is divided into two categories, Personal and Third Party. Personal reports were written by Morris herself and were usually notes taken during meetings, drafts of weekly reports, and expense reports. Third party reports include copies of correspondence between two other parties, collected by Morris for information purposes. This category also includes reports on current events and transcripts of meetings and speeches. Third party reports are divided by country and subject.
American Federation of Labor. Free Trade Union Committee.; Lovestone, Jay.; Labor unions and communism.
- Correspondence, 1950-1984 (Box-folder 1:1-2:4)
  - Lovestone Correspondence, 1950-1983 (Box-folder 1:1-2:3)
    - 1950-1953 (Box-folder 1:1-2)
    - 1954-1955 (Box-folder 1:3-4)
    - 1955-1960 (Box-folder 1:5-6)
    - 1961-1964 (Box-folder 2:2)
    - 1964-1969 (Box-folder 2:3)
    - 1976-1983 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - General Correspondence, 1950-1984 (Box-folder 1:8-2:4)
    - 1950-1957 (Box-folder 1:8)
    - 1952-1967 (Box-folder 2:4)
    - 1957-1984 (Box-folder 2:1)
- Reports, 1950-1958 (Box-folder 2:5-3:8)
  - Personal Reports, 1956-1958 (Box-folder 2:5-2:11)
    - Meeting notes and daily journal, undated (Box-folder 2:5)
    - Expense reports, meeting notes, speech transcript, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 2:6)
    - Weekly reports and correspondence, 1956 (Box-folder 2:8)
    - Personal notes, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 2:9)
    - Intelligence reports, undated (Box-folder 2:11)
  - Third Party Reports, 1950-1957 (Box-folder 2:7-3:8)
    - Copies, correspondence “American Federation of Labor” and Cairo, 1952-1956 (Box-folder 2:7)
    - Asian Socialist Conference, 1956 (Box-folder 2:10)
    - Correspondence and reports: labor parties and communism, 1956-1957 (Box-folder 2:12)
    - Reports and correspondence: Israel, 1952-1953 (Box-folder 3:1)
    - Reports and correspondence: India, 1950-1957 (Box-folder 3:2)
    - Manuscript: Kashmir, reports: India, Undated (Box-folder 3:3)
    - Report: Tibet, 1951 (Box-folder 3:4)
    - Correspondence and reports: Hungary and Bulgaria, 1951-1953 (Box-folder 3:5)
    - Reports: Soviet Union, 1951 (Box-folder 3:6)
    - “Committee for Free Asia,", 1953 (Box-folder 3:7)
    - General reports, 1951-1952 (Box-folder 3:8)